(Video: Air traffic controller directs traffic) This is our air traffic controller calling it in to Kigali International Airport. And when the Zip arrives at the hospital, it descends to about 30 feet and drops the package. We use a really simple paper parachute -- simple things are best -- that allows the package to come to the ground gently and reliably in the same place every time. So it's just like ride sharing; the doctors get a text message one minute before we arrive, saying, "Walk outside and receive your delivery." (Laughter) And then -- (Applause) and then the doctors have what they need to save a patient's life. This is actually watching a delivery happen from our distribution center; this vehicle is about 50 kilometers away. We're able to watch the vehicle as it makes a delivery at a hospital in real time. You may have noticed there are pings that are coming off of that vehicle on the screen. Those pings are actually data packets that we're getting over the cell phone networks. So these planes have SIM cards just like your cell phone does, and they're communicating over the cell network to tell us where they are and how they're doing at all times. Believe it or not, we actually buy family plans -- (Laughter) for this fleet of vehicles, because that's how we get the best rates. (Laughter) It's actually not a joke. So today, we're delivering about 20 percent of the national blood supply of Rwanda outside of Kigali. We serve about 12 hospitals, and we're adding hospitals to that network at an accelerating rate. All of those hospitals only receive blood in this way, and most of those hospitals actually place multiple orders every day. So the reason -- in all of health care logistics, you're always trading off waste against access. So if you want to solve waste, you keep everything centralized. As a result, when patients are having emergencies, sometimes they don't have the medical product they need. If you want to solve access, you stock a lot of medicine at the last mile, at hospitals or health centers, and then patients have the medicine they need. But you end up throwing a lot of medicine out, which is very expensive. What's so amazing is that the Rwandan government has been able to break this cycle permanently. Because doctors can get what they need instantly, they actually stock less blood at the hospitals. So although use of blood products has increased substantially at all the hospitals we serve, in the last nine months, zero units of blood have expired at any of these hospitals. (Applause) That's an amazing result. That's actually not been achieved by any other health care system on the planet, and it happened here. But obviously, when we're talking about delivering medical products instantly, the most important thing is patients. Let me give you an example. A couple months ago, a 24-year-old mother came into one of the hospitals that we serve, and she gave birth via C-section. But that led to complications, and she started to bleed. Luckily, the doctors had some blood of her blood type on hand that had been delivered via Zipline's routine service, and so they transfused her with a couple units of blood. But she bled out of those units in about 10 minutes. In this case, that mother's life is in grave danger -- in any hospital in the world. But luckily, the doctors who were taking care of her immediately called our distribution center, they placed an emergency order, and our team actually did emergency delivery after emergency delivery after emergency delivery. They ended up sending seven units of red blood cells, four units of plasma and two units of platelets. That's more blood than you have in your entire body. All of it was transfused into her, the doctors were able to stabilize her, and she is healthy today. (Applause) Since we launched, we've done about 400 emergency deliveries like that, and there's a story like that one behind most of those emergencies. Here are just a couple of the moms who have received transfusions in this way in the last couple months. We're always reminded: when we can help a doctor save a mom's life, it's not just her life that you're saving. That's also a baby boy or a baby girl who has a mother while they're growing up. (Applause) But I want to be clear: postpartum hemorrhaging -- it's not a Rwanda problem, it's not a developing-world problem -- this is a global problem. Maternal health is a challenge everywhere. The main difference is that Rwanda was the first country to use radical technology to do something about it. And that's the reason this attitude of Africa being disrupted or advanced technology not working here or needing aid is so totally wrong. Africa can be the disrupter. These small, agile, developing economies can out-innovate large, rich ones. And they can totally leapfrog over the absence of legacy infrastructure to go straight to newer and better systems. In 2000, if you had said that high-quality cellular networks were about to roll out across all of Africa, people would have told you that you were crazy. And yet, no one anticipated how fast those networks were going to connect and empower people. Today, 44 percent of the GDP of Kenya flows through M-Pesa, their mobile payment platform. And not only that, but our autonomous fleet of vehicles relies on that cellular network. Over the next few years as we start serving private health care facilities, we'll also use that mobile payment platform to collect fees for deliveries. So innovation leads to more innovation leads to more innovation. And meanwhile, most people who live in developed economies think that drone delivery is technologically impossible, let alone happening at national scale in East Africa. And I do mean East Africa, not just Rwanda. On Thursday, just a couple days ago, the Tanzanian Ministry of Health announced that they are going to use this same technology to provide instant delivery of a wide range of medical products to 10 million of the hardest to reach people in the country. (Applause) It's actually going to be the largest autonomous system anywhere in the world. To give you a sense of what this looks like, this is one of the first distribution centers. You can see a 75-kilometer service radius around the distribution center, and that allows us to serve hundreds of health facilities and hospitals, all of which are rural, from that single distribution center. But to serve over 20 percent of the population of Tanzania, we're going to need multiple distribution centers. We'll actually need four. And from these distribution centers, we expect to be doing several hundred lifesaving deliveries every day, and this system will ultimately serve over 1,000 health facilities and hospitals in the country. So yeah, East Africa is moving really fast. One thing that people, I think, often miss is that these kinds of leaps generate compounding gains. For example, Rwanda, by investing in this infrastructure for health care, now has an aerial logistics network that they can use to catalyze other parts of their economy, like agriculture or e-commerce. Even more importantly, 100 percent of the teams we hire at these distribution centers are local. So here's our Rwandan team, which is a group of extraordinary engineers and operators. They run the world's only automated delivery system operating at national scale. They have been able to master something that the largest technology companies in the world have not yet been able to figure out. So they are total heroes. (Applause) They're total heroes. Our team's mission is to deliver basic access to medicine to all seven billion people on the planet, no matter how hard it is to reach them. We often tell people about that mission, and they say, "That's so generous of you, it's so philanthropic." No! Philanthropy has nothing to do with it. Because of the commercial contracts that we sign with ministries of health, these networks are 100 percent sustainable and scalable. And the reason we feel so strongly about correcting that misperception is that entrepreneurship is the only force in human history that has lifted millions of people out of poverty. (Applause) No amount of foreign aid is going to sustainably employ 250 million African youth. And the jobs that these kids may have gotten 10 years ago are largely being automated or are being changed dramatically by technology. So they are looking for new skill sets, new competitive advantages. They're looking for start-ups. So why aren't there more start-ups that are tackling these global problems that are faced by billions of people in developing economies? The reason is that investors and entrepreneurs are totally blind to the opportunity. We think these problems are the domain of NGOs or governments, not private companies. That's what we have to change. You may have noticed I left something out of the video that I showed you. I didn't show you how the planes land when they get back to the distribution center. So, it might be obvious to you: none of our planes have landing gear. We also don't have runways where we operate. So we have to be able to decelerate the plane from about 100 kilometers an hour to zero in half of a second. And the way we do that is we actually use a wire that tracks that plane as it comes in, with centimeter-level accuracy. We snag the plane out of the sky, and then we gently plop it onto an actively inflated cushion. This is basically a combination of an aircraft carrier and a bouncy castle. (Laughter) So let me show you. (Applause) And it might be obvious to you why I wanted to end with this video. I wanted to show you the kids and the teenagers who line up on the fence every day. They cheer every launch and every landing. (Laughter) (Applause) Sometimes I actually show up at the distribution center early because I'm jet-lagged. I'll show up an hour before we begin operation. And there will be kids on the fence getting good seats. (Laughter) And you go up and you ask them, "What do you think about the planes?" And they'll say, "Oh, it's a sky ambulance." So they get it. I mean, they get it more than most adults. So I was asking earlier: Who is going to be creating the disruptive technology companies of Africa over the next decade? Ultimately, it's going to be up to these kids. They are the engineers of Rwanda and Africa. They are the engineers of our shared future. But the only way they can build that future is if we realize that world-changing companies can scale in Africa, and that disruptive technology can start here first. Thanks. (Applause)
(Video: el controlador de tráfico aéreo dirige el tráfico) Este es nuestro controlador de tránsito aéreo que llama al aeropuerto internacional de Kigali. Y cuando el zip llega al hospital, desciende a unos 9 m y deja caer el paquete. Usamos un paracaídas de papel muy simple. Las cosas simples son las mejores. Eso permite que el paquete llegue al suelo de forma suave y confiable en el mismo lugar todo el tiempo. Es como compartir el viaje; los médicos reciben un mensaje un minuto antes de que lleguemos, que dice: "Salga y reciba su entrega". (Risa) Y entonces... (Aplausos) luego los médicos tienen lo necesario para salvar la vida de un paciente. Esto es la vista de una entrega desde nuestro centro de distribución; este vehículo está a unos 50 km de distancia. Podemos ver el vehículo mientras realiza una entrega en un hospital en tiempo real. Quizá hayan notado que hay pings, rastreadores de paquetes en redes, que salen de ese vehículo en la pantalla. Esos pings son, en realidad, paquetes de datos que usan las redes de telefonía móvil. Estos aviones tienen tarjetas SIM al igual que un teléfono móvil, y se comunican a través de la red móvil para decirnos dónde y cómo están en todo momento. Lo crean o no, en realidad, compramos planes familiares (Risas) para esta flota de vehículos, porque así es como obtenemos las mejores tarifas. (Risas) En realidad, no es una broma. Así que en la actualidad entregamos un 20 % del suministro nacional de sangre de Ruanda fuera de Kigali. Servimos a unos 12 hospitales, y estamos agregando hospitales a esa red a un ritmo acelerado. Todos esos hospitales solo reciben sangre de esta manera, y la mayoría de esos hospitales hacen pedidos múltiples todos los días. Entonces la razón en toda la logística del cuidado de la salud, siempre se intercambia desperdicio por acceso. Si se quiere resolver lo del desperdicio, hay que mantener todo centralizado. Como resultado, cuando los pacientes tienen emergencias, a veces no tienen el producto médico que necesitan. Si se quiere resolver el acceso, hay muchos medicamentos en el último km, en hospitales o centros de salud, y así los pacientes tienen los medicamentos que necesitan. Pero se terminan tirando muchos medicamentos, que es muy caro Lo sorprendente es que el gobierno de Ruanda ha sido capaz de romper este ciclo de forma permanente. Porque los médicos pueden obtener lo que necesitan al instante, en realidad, almacenan menos sangre en los hospitales. Y, aunque el uso de productos sanguíneos ha aumentado sustancialmente en todos los hospitales que atendemos, en los últimos nueve meses, cero unidades de sangre han expirado en cualquiera de estos hospitales. (Aplausos) Ese es un resultado sorprendente. Eso en realidad no se ha logrado en ningún otro sistema de atención médica en el planeta, y sucedió aquí. Pero obviamente, cuando hablamos de entregar productos médicos al instante, lo más importante son los pacientes. Les daré un ejemplo. Hace un par de meses, una madre de 24 años entró en uno de los hospitales a los que atendemos, y dio a luz por cesárea. Y eso llevó a complicaciones y comenzó a sangrar. Afortunadamente, los médicos tenían sangre de su tipo sanguíneo a mano que se había entregado mediante el servicio de Zipline, y le transfundieron un par de unidades de sangre. Pero ella sangró esas unidades en unos 10 minutos. En este caso la vida de esa madre estaría en grave peligro en cualquier hospital del mundo. Pero afortunadamente, los médicos que la cuidaban llamaron de inmediato a nuestro centro de distribución, emitiendo un pedido de emergencia, y nuestro equipo hizo entrega de emergencia tras entrega de emergencia, tras entrega de emergencia. Al final se enviaron siete unidades de glóbulos rojos, cuatro unidades de plasma y dos unidades de plaquetas. Eso es más sangre de la que tienes en todo tu cuerpo. Toda se le transfundió a ella, los médicos pudieron estabilizarla, y ella está sana hoy. (Aplausos) Desde que empezamos, hemos realizado unas 400 entregas de emergencia como esa, y hay una historia como esa detrás de la mayoría de esas emergencias. Aquí hay solo un par de las mamás que han recibido transfusiones de esta manera en los últimos meses. Siempre nos recuerdan: al ayudar a un médico a salvar la vida de una madre, no es solo su vida lo que estás salvando, también se salva la vida de un bebé o una beba que tiene una madre mientras crece. (Aplausos) Pero quiero ser claro: la hemorragia posparto no es un problema de Ruanda, no es un problema del mundo en desarrollo, es un problema global. La salud materna es un desafío en todas partes. La principal diferencia es que Ruanda fue el primer país en usar tecnología radical para hacer algo al respecto. Y esa es la razón por la cual esta actitud de que en África no funcione la tecnología avanzada o de que necesitan ayuda es totalmente errónea. África puede ser el disruptor. Estas economías pequeñas, ágiles y en desarrollo pueden superar la innovación de las grandes y ricas. Y pueden superar por completo la ausencia de infraestructura heredada y lanzarse directamente a sistemas nuevos y mejores. En 2000, si alguien hubiera dicho que las redes móviles de alta calidad estaban a punto de desplegarse en toda África, la gente habría dicho que estábamos locos. Y, sin embargo, nadie anticipó lo rápido que esas redes se conectarían y empoderarían a las personas. Hoy el 44 % del PIB de Kenia fluye a través de M-Pesa, su plataforma de pago móvil. Y no solo eso, también nuestra flota autónoma de vehículos se basa en esa red móvil. En los próximos años a medida que prestemos servicios privados de atención médica, también usaremos esa plataforma de pago móvil para cobrar tarifas por entregas. Y la innovación lleva a mayor innovación y a más innovación. Y, mientras tanto, la mayoría de las personas que viven en economías desarrolladas piensa que la entrega de drones es tecnológicamente imposible, y más imposible que suceda a escala nacional en el este de África. Y me refiero al este de África, no solo a Ruanda. El jueves, hace solo un par de días, el Ministerio de Salud de Tanzania anunció que van a usar esta misma tecnología para proporcionar una entrega instantánea de una amplia gama de productos médicos a 10 millones de las personas con más difícil acceso en el país. (Aplausos) En realidad, va a ser el sistema autónomo más grande del mundo. Para darles una idea de cómo se ve esto, este es uno de los primeros centros de distribución. Puede ver un radio de servicio de 75 km alrededor del centro de distribución, y eso nos permite servir a cientos de centros de salud y hospitales, todos ellos rurales, desde ese centro de distribución único. Pero para servir a más del 20 % de la población de Tanzania, vamos a necesitar varios centros de distribución, realmente necesitaremos cuatro. Y desde estos centros de distribución, esperamos hacer cientos de entregas de salvamento todos los días, y este sistema finalmente dará servicio a más de 1000 instalaciones de salud y hospitales en el país. Así que sí, el este de África se mueve muy rápido. Una cosa que las personas, a menudo, no saben es que este tipo de saltos generan ganancias capitalizables. Ruanda, al invertir en esta infraestructura del cuidado de salud, ahora tiene una red de logística aérea que puede usar para catalizar otras partes de su economía, como la agricultura o el comercio electrónico. Aún más importante, el 100 % de los equipos que contratamos en estos centros de distribución son locales. Así que aquí está nuestro equipo de Ruanda, que es un grupo de ingenieros y operadores extraordinarios. Manejan el único sistema de entrega automatizado del mundo que opera a escala nacional. Han sido capaces de dominar algo que las empresas de tecnología más grandes del mundo todavía no han podido descifrar. Son héroes totales. (Aplausos) La misión de nuestro equipo es brindar acceso básico a la medicina a los 7000 millones de personas del planeta, no importa cuán difícil sea alcanzarlos. A menudo contamos a la gente sobre esa misión, y dicen: "Eso es muy generoso de su parte, es muy filantrópico". ¡No! La filantropía no tiene nada que ver con eso. Debido a los contratos comerciales que firmamos con ministerios de salud, estas redes son 100 % sostenibles y expandibles. Y la razón para sentirnos tan enojados al corregir esa percepción errónea es que el emprendimiento es la única fuerza en la historia humana que ha sacado a millones de personas de la pobreza. (Aplausos) Ninguna ayuda extranjera va a emplear de forma sostenible a 250 millones de jóvenes africanos. Y los trabajos que estos niños pudieron haber recibido hace 10 años se están automatizando en gran medida o están siendo cambiados drásticamente por la tecnología. Y buscan nuevas habilidades, nuevas ventajas competitivas. Buscan nuevas empresas. Y ¿por qué no hay más nuevas empresas abordando estos problemas globales que enfrentan miles de millones de personas en las economías en desarrollo? La razón es que los inversores y emprendedores están totalmente ciegos a la oportunidad. Creemos que estos problemas pertenecen a ONGs o a gobiernos, no a compañías privadas. Eso es lo que tenemos que cambiar. Es posible que hayan notado que dejé algo fuera del video que les mostré. No enseñé cómo aterrizan los aviones cuando regresen al centro de distribución. Y puede que sea obvio para Uds. Ninguno de nuestros aviones tiene tren de aterrizaje. Tampoco tenemos pistas donde operamos. Y debemos poder desacelerar el avión de unos 100 km por hora a cero en medio segundo. Y la forma en que hacemos eso es usando un cable que rastrea ese avión cuando entra con precisión a nivel de centrímetros. Agarramos el avión del cielo, y luego lo colocamos suavemente sobre un cojín inflado activamente. Esto es una combinación de un portaaviones y un castillo hinchable. (Risas) Se los mostraré. (Aplausos) Y podría ser obvio por qué quería terminar con este video. Quería mostrarles a los niños y los adolescentes que se alinean en la cerca todos los días. Ellos animan cada lanzamiento y cada aterrizaje. (Risas) (Aplausos) A veces voy temprano al centro de distribución porque tengo jet lag. Y aparezco una hora antes de comenzar la operación. Y ya hay niños en la cerca reservando buenos asientos. (Risas) Y uno sube y les pregunta: "¿Qué piensan de los aviones?" Y dicen: "Es una ambulancia del cielo". Lo entienden. Quiero decir, lo entienden mejor que la mayoría de los adultos. Antes pregunté: ¿Quién va a crear las empresas de tecnología disruptiva de África en la próxima década? En última instancia, va a depender de estos niños. Ellos son los ingenieros de Ruanda y África. Ellos son los ingenieros de nuestro futuro compartido. Pero la única forma en que pueden construir ese futuro es si entendemos que las empresas que cambian el mundo pueden expandirse en África, y esa tecnología disruptiva puede comenzar aquí primero. Gracias. (Aplausos)